<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning unto apostates &amp; backsliders that formerly have made a profession of the truth, but walk not answerably thereunto but are crucifying to themselves afresh the Son of God, and putting him unto open shame, and thereby are treasuring up wrath against the day of wrath, and revelation of the reighteous judgements of the Lord : also a visitation and warning to all workers of iniquity, that they may repent and turn to the Lord with speed, before his dreadful judgments be poured forth upon them / by Richard Stubbs.</title>
            <author>Stubbs, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12281527</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12281527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58717</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58717)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning unto apostates &amp; backsliders that formerly have made a profession of the truth, but walk not answerably thereunto but are crucifying to themselves afresh the Son of God, and putting him unto open shame, and thereby are treasuring up wrath against the day of wrath, and revelation of the reighteous judgements of the Lord : also a visitation and warning to all workers of iniquity, that they may repent and turn to the Lord with speed, before his dreadful judgments be poured forth upon them / by Richard Stubbs.</title>
                  <author>Stubbs, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58717:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58717:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING UNTO Apoſtates &amp; Backsliders, That formerly have made a Profeſsion of the <hi>Truth,</hi> but walk not <hi>anſwerably</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>But are crucifying to themſelves afreſh the Son of God, and putting him unto open Shame, and thereby are treaſuring up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righteous Judgments of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Alſo A Viſitation and Warning To all Workers of Iniquity, that they may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and Turn to the Lord with ſpeed, before his Dreadful Judgments be poured forth upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Richard Stubbs.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58717:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58717:2"/>
            <head>A WARNING UNTO ALL Apoſtates &amp; Backsliders, That formerly have made a Profeſsion of the <hi>Truth,</hi> but walk not <hi>anſwerably</hi> thereunto, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving been Convinced of God's Everlaſting Truth, which is Chriſt Jeſus, the Light of the World, which lightens every one coming into the World, which is the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, a Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening Spirit; the which Light and Spirit, a meaſure thereof is given unto all, and appears unto all, whereby the Lord is clear of the Blood of all that periſh in ſin; for their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is of themſelves, as the Lord hath ſaid in Ages paſt, <hi>Your Destruction is of your ſelves, but in me is your Help:</hi> For the Light of Chriſt, or Grace of God, that brings Salvation, hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and does at this very day appear unto all in their Hearts and Inward Parts, which is a Diſcerner of the Thoughts and Intents of the Heart, and makes manifeſt ſin, and is of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Heavenly Nature, and hath no Fellowſhip with Darkneſs, but leads out of Darkneſs, and teaches all that give up to be taught by it, <hi>To deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, and to live Soberly, Righteouſly and Godly in this preſent Evil World.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58717:3"/>
            <p>And hereby the Works of Darkneſs, and the Old Man with his Deeds come to be put off, and the New Man to be put on, which is renewed in Knowledg after the Image of him that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated him; and here no proviſion is made for the Fleſh, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the Luſt thereof: and ſo let none live in Rioting and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, nor be Over-charged with the Care of this Life, nor Cumber their Minds with the many things, whereby many are intangled and inſnared by the Net of the Cunning Hunter, who goes about ſeeking whom he may Devour; and as many as are inſnared by him, are off their Watch, and are not wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Light of the Lord in their own particulars, and ſo are neither ſenſible of the Lord's Preſence, nor yet the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Evil One, whereby many live as without God in the World, and ſo are Dead while they Live, and ſo are Unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Lord, having not a Senſe of the Lord's Preſence, being gone from his Appearance in their own particulars, and ſo caſt the Law of God behind their backs; and as many as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard and reject that Light in their own Conſciences, which appears againſt ſin, they reject the Lord, and caſt his Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their backs; and ſo, when the Preſence of the Lord is not minded, nor his Light taken heed unto, then Darkneſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails, and the Worker of Iniquity enters, and ſows his Seed, as it was ſaid, <hi>While Men ſlept the Enemy ſow'd his Tares:</hi> But this is the Day of God's Harveſt, wherein he is bundling up the Tares for the Fire of his Wrath, and making a Separation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Precious and the Vile, and is gathering the Wheat into his Garner, where the Enemy cannot enter: And the Lord is a ſure Refuge to as many as believe in his Light, and ſtay their Minds upon him, and is a preſent help in time of Trouble.</p>
            <p>I ſay, When ſin appears, when Iniquity would prevail and bear Rule, then by all that believe in Chriſt, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of the World, is the Standard of the Lord lifted up againſt the Man of ſin, and in the Sttength of the Lord are his Temptations repell'd, and beaten back; and ſo the Lord is known and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be a preſent. Help in time of Trouble by a Remnant that at this day have their Minds in ſome meaſure turned from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58717:3"/>Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto the Power of God.</p>
            <p>But I was captivated and overcome of the Evil one, by not waiting upon the Lord, nor having the Loins of my Mind girded up unto the Light, that ſhines in the Heart, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears againſt Evil; nor having my Mind exerciſed in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus (in my own Heart) at all times; ſo for want of this, a light and airy ſpirit begun to prevail, and grew up, whereby the Faithful and True Witneſs lay ſlain, as I may ſay, in the great City, which ſpiritually is called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where alſo the Lord was crucified, and is crucified and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at this day, as in Dayes and Ages that are by-paſt and gone, by all thoſe that art eating and drinking with the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and live Wantonly upon Earth: For ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> is within in the Heart, and ſpiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> is within all thoſe that keep the Seed in Bondage, and that will not let it ariſe: And ſo all they that are walking contrary to the Light in their own Conſciences, which appears againſt ſin, they are crucifying the Lord, and grieving his holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>But Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord forever, who is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in Long ſuffering and Mercy, and is not willing any ſhould dye in their ſins; for, whoever dye in ſin, whither Chriſt goes thither they never ſhall come: But the Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs of the Lord is extended, and his Light hath deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the Lord hath reached forth a Hand of Love, and Arm of Salvation, and vouchſafed Help to the Helpleſs, even to as many as take heed to the Light in their own Hearts, and ſtay their Mind, upon the Lord, do witneſs the fulfilling the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Lord, <hi>That they ſhould look upon him whom they had pierced, and mourn over him:</hi> And bleſſed be the Lord forever, for his Mercy and tender Loving-kindneſs; there is a Remnant at this day, who have turned the Eye of their Minds unto Chriſt, the Light of the World, whom they have pierced in their own particulars (as well as others) and have mourned over him, and are now in ſome meaſure walking in the Light of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And Bleſſed and Magnified be the Name of the Lord forever and for evermore, who hath in meaſure inclined my Heart to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58717:4"/>wait upon him, that ſo I may be inabled to withſtand the Appearance of Evil, and the Temptations of the Evil One, who by his ſubtil Workings and cunning Devices, ſeeks to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare and intangle as many as are off their Watch, and not minding the Appearance of Truth in their own Hearts, which never tempteth any Man to Evil, nor conſented unto Sin: but the Evil is judged and condemned by the Light which ſhines in the Hearts of all, to diſcover Sin, and to lead out of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo to Chriſt reconciling Man unto God again, who is an Enemy unto God by reaſon of Wicked Works; for Sin ſeparates between God and Man, let their Profeſſion be what it will; without Holineſs of Life it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: the Profeſſion of the Truth it ſelf will little avail any without the Poſſeſſion thereof, it will but increaſe their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; but they that walk in the Light, and mind the Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus in their own Hearts, theſe come to have Fellowſhip with the Lord: And here I ſpeak not of things at a Diſtance, or becauſe it is thus written, but what I find in my own particular to be true.</p>
            <p>And as a Holy, Harmleſs, Innocent Life comes again to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and grow up: So Favour with the Lord and Communion and Fellowſhip with the Light of Jeſus, and alſo with as many as walk therein again comes to be witneſſed, and ſo in a Holy Innocent Life ſtands the Communion of Saints, and here the Forgiveneſs of Sins that are paſt is known, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body out of Sin witneſſed, even from Death unto Life, from the Death of Sin unto the Life of Righteouſneſs, the which is loſt by Sinning againſt the Lord, and walking contrary to the Light; for ſo I muſt call it; for in it is no Darkneſs at all; I never yet found any, though many through the Darkneſs of their Minds and Hardneſs of their Hearts are ready to charge the Sins and Backſlidings of them that profeſs the Truth and Light upon the Truth and Light it ſelf: and ſo many are ſaying, We may ſee what your Light is; And ſo are ſpeaking Evil of a Thing they know not, and ſo are Blaſpheming God, and his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven.</p>
            <p>But unto all ſuch I teſtifie and declare, and it is my Teſtimony
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58717:4"/>for the Lord, that the Light which condemns Sin in the Heart, never yet did, and it is my Belief never will lead into any Sin; but when I was off my Watch, and was not waiting upon the Lord, to be ordered and ruled by him, then I was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times eating and drinking with the Drunken, and ſo was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying to my ſelf afreſh the Son of God, and putting him unto open Shame, even as Ages have done and are doing, that are eating and drinking with the Drunken, and living wantonly upon the Earth, and are crucifying the Juſt in their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: And herein was I captivated by Sin, and Peace with the Lord I knew not; but Tribulation and Wrath from the Lord ſeized upon me becauſe of Sin, for I was diſobeying the Lord, and ſo in that State, as I may ſay, was ſhut out from the Lord's Preſence and Favour, and at every Entrance was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Flaming Sword, which the Lord hath placed for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Man of Sin, and for the cutting down the Diſobedient Nature, and none can enter or come to enjoy Peace with the Lord again, but as that which hath ſeparated and been as a Partition-Wall be taken out of the Way; and ſo an Entrance is adminiſtred again, as the Man of Sin comes to be ſlain by the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God which is Quick, Powerful and Sharper then any two-edged Sword, piercing even to the Dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit, and is a Diſcerner of the Thoughts and Intents of the Heart.</p>
            <p>And ſo at this Day, Bleſſed be the Lord, there is a Remnant that know the Word of the Lord to be as a Sword with two Edges, that cuts every Way, even to the dividing between their Souls and that Spirit of Darkneſs that would not have Chriſt to reign.</p>
            <p>And alſo know the Word of the Lord to be as a Fire, even as a Conſuming-Fire in their own Particulars, and ſo come to know the Briers and Thorns to be burnt and burning up, that ſo Way may be made for the Seed to come forth to the Praiſe and Glory of the Lord, that ſo his Name may be renowned and magnified above and over all (the Powers of Darkneſs) whole Majeſty is moſt Excellent and his Glory to be exalted above and over all that is Mortal, and over all ſpirits of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58717:5"/>Darkneſs, and over the Prince of the Power of the Air that now rules in thoſe that rebel againſt the Light of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And a Remnant that have believed in the Light, and in ſome Meaſure are walking therein, do know the Way of the Lord to burn as an Oven which burns up the Wood, the Bryars, and Thorns, and ſo in ſome Meaſure are come to witneſs the Man of Sin to be deſtroyed, even by the Appearance of Chriſt the Light in the Heart, and by the Brightneſs of its ſhining forth, whoſe Glory and Brightneſs ſhall yet ſhine forth, even to the Abaſement of all Worldly Glory and Greatneſs, and to the Dazelling of the Eyes of the <hi>Heathen;</hi> for the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to exalt his Truth, and ſet his King upon his Holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and as many as cleave unto the Lord ſhall live and reign with him; but whoever denyes him, ſhall be denyed Admittance into Heaven; and the Joy and Peace which is Spiritual, and that abides forever, they ſhall never come to witneſs, who vilifie the Light of Chriſt Jeſus; and whoever rebell againſt its Holy Command and Heavenly Operation, all ſuch forſake the Fountain of Living Waters, and hew unto themſelves broken Ceſterns, that can hold no Water; But unto as many as wait for his Appearance, and obey his Holy Call, they come to witneſs the Day of the Lord to burn as an Oven, and all that is Unrighteous to be conſumed or conſuming, and the Unclean Spirit to be driven or driving out of the Land; and ſo come to know the Heavens to paſs away (with a great Noiſe, and the Elements to melt with fervent Heat, the Earth alſo and the Works that are therein to be burnt up in this Day of the Lord's Appearance) in their own particulars, and ſo are not like the Profeſſors, who are looking for a Day which conſiſts of 12. Hours, or ſo, wherein all the Outward Fabrick of this viſible World, and things therein, ſhould be on Fire, but are come to witneſs, and in their Meaſures to teſtifie unto the World, that the Day of God is come, wherein he is ſetting Fire to the Earthly Part in Man, and the Works that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wrought, that ſo he may make Way for the Seed of the Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Kingdom to take root downward in the Hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men and Women, that ſo the Fruit of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs may be brought forth to the Praiſe and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58717:5"/>Honour of him who is carrying on this Bleſſed Work in this the Day of his Appearance; and ſo know in Meaſure the New Heaven and the New Earth, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs; and the Tabernacle of God is with Men, as he hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and they ſhall be my People, and I will be their God.</p>
            <p>But ſo long as I was captivated by Sin, though profeſſing the Truth, yet Peace with the Lord I knew not, neither was there any Stedfaſtneſs in my going, but was hurried up and down as with a Tempeſt by the Prince of the Power of the Air, that now works in the Children of Diſobedience, who are either Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Light, or have turned their Backs upon it, and reject it: As the Lord hath complained in dayes paſt, of ſome <hi>who caſt his Law behind their Backs, and would none of his Counſel;</hi> and ſo by Sinning againſt the Lord, I was treaſuring up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righteous Judgments of the Lord, which will certainly come upon all the Workers of Iniquity, that are Diſobedient unto the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of God's Holy Spirit in their own Hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; a Meaſure of which Spirit and Light God hath vouchſafed unto all, which reproves all, and waits upon all, and invites all to come unto him and be ſaved; and ſo if any periſh in Sin, their Deſtruction is of themſelves; for the Lord waits upon all, that he may be gracious; that that appears againſt Evil and Sin in the Hearts of all, if it be minded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in and waited upon, it will lead out of Sin.</p>
            <p>And having known the Terrors of the Lord, and the Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Almighty, becauſe of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, and for Sinning againſt the Lord, I do warn all, and exhort all to mind the Day of their Viſitation, and not to ſlight God's Love; but while it is called to day, harden not your Hearts againſt that that reproves, but bow to the Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus in your own particulars; for this is the Day of God's Love, wherein he is ſtretching forth a Hand and Arm of Love and Salvation unto all.</p>
            <p>So let all bow unto the Scepter of Chriſt Jeſus, that ſo Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and cleanſing from Sin on this ſide the Grave thou mayeſt come to witneſs; for as the Tree falls ſo it lyes, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58717:6"/>there is no Work nor Device in the Grave, whither we are all very ſhortly going; therefore mind the Lord, and walk in the Light of the Lamb, and obey the Lord in all things; for every one muſt receive according to his Works, and according to this Deeds done in the Body: for the Lord will not condemn the Righteous, nor clear the Guilty, though the Profeſſors of this Age hold forth and believe ſuch a thing, and ſo are wreſting Scriptures to their own Deſtruction; and they ſay, That though we are polluted in our ſelves, and full of Wounds and Bruiſes, yet God looks upon us in Chriſt Jeſus as righteous, and that he will look upon Perſons that are polluted with Sin, as in themſelves, yet to be Righteous as in Chriſt at the ſame time, while polluted with Sin as in themſelves, and ſo are imagining a Righteouſneſs by Way of Imputation, as they call it; but this Device will not avail any; but all muſt really come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Chriſt's Righteouſneſs wrought in them, and the Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs wrought out, and ſo to walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit, and ſo come to witneſs the Strong Man that hath kept the Houſe to be diſpoſſeſſed, and his Goods to be ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by one that is Stronger then he, which is Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, who is the Wiſdom of God and the Power of God to as many as believe in him, and obey him in all things.</p>
            <p>Now this is a Buſineſs of the greateſt Importance and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, inaſmuch as the Soul is of an Immortal Being, and muſt live or be Eternally either in Joy and Felicity, or elſe in Wo and Torment forever and evermore; a Condition never to be altred, never to be changed; therefore let all and every one of us mind the Work which lyes before us, and work out every one his own Salvation with Fear and Trembling, <hi>for it is God that worketh in us to will and to do of his own Good Pleaſure;</hi> and let not any of us ſpend that little time we are yet to remain (in theſe Houſes of Clay) in Vanity and Folly, in Rioting and Drunkenneſs; but mind the Grace of God that brings Salvation, and appears unto all, and teaches all that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be taught by it, to deny Ungodlineſs, and Worldly Luſt, and to live ſoberly and godly in this preſent Evil World.</p>
            <p>Now the Evil One, who is called the <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58717:6"/>Enemy of Man kind, endeavours to keep all Hearts and Minds upon Viſible, Fading, Periſhing things, which are but for a very ſhort Seaſon, and the Glory and Beauty thereof muſt periſh and fade away; and ſo preſenting the Glory of this preſent World, and the Delights therein, endeavours thereby to keep all from worſhipping and ſerving the Lord in Spirit and Truth, and ſo out of the Sence of an Eternal State and Being, and from liſtening to the Voice of Chriſt Jeſus, which is neer at the Heart, that waits upon all, to lead out of Sin, and ſo to bring into Fellowſhip with God again.</p>
            <p>But ſo long as I was captivated by Sin, and was not walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Light of the Lord, ſo I came to ſtumble and fall; for he that ſtumbles ſtumbles in the Night, and they that are drunk are drunk in the Night; and ſo here I was not regarding the Voice of the Lord, nor walking in his Fear; but was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the Light, though the Lord by his gentle Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections did ſpeak once, yea twice, yet I regarded not his Call, but was even as a Bullock unaccuſtomed to the Yoak, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of receiving Correction, I was oftentimes ready to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur againſt the Lord, and repine at his Fatherly Chaſtize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though the true and faithful Witneſs did oftentimes ariſe in my Heart, and was a ſwift Witneſs againſt every thing that was Evil, and this did ſhew unto me that I had ſinned againſt the Lord, and therefore his Hand was ſtretched out againſt me, and the Lord followed me with his Judgments, and his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are Righteous altogether, and this was the Lord's Love, Bleſſed and Magnified be his Name for ever; <hi>for before I was afflicted I went aſtray,</hi> but now in ſome Meaſure am obeying the Voice of the Lord, and herein Peace is witneſſed, which is not to be found in the Way of Sin.</p>
            <p>And oftentimes I did reſolve in my Mind to be more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Lord, but not looking unto him, ſo Salvation from Sin I fell ſhort of: So Sin prevalled, and I was led Captive by the Evil One, by not giving Heed unto the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which ſhined in my Heart, and appeared againſt Sin.</p>
            <p>But as my Mind came again in ſome meaſure to be retired, and waiting upon the Light, which reproves for Sin, ſo I found
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58717:7"/>Strength in ſome Meaſure to withſtand Sin; and ſo, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as wait upon the Lord will be kept out of Defilement, and Sin, and Pollution, and ſo in perfect Peace with the Lord; for there is no Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit, that walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Guidance and Direction of the Spirit, a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of which is given unto all to profit withal, which Spirit of Life and Light is given to be a Light to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to be God's Salvation to the Ends of the Earth, and none need ſay in their Hearts, who ſhall aſcend or deſcend to bring him up again from the Dead, or bring him down from above? for <hi>the Word is nigh, even in the Heart and Mouth, that we may hear it, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not giving up in all things unto this divine Light which appears in the Heart againſt Sin, which Light never conſented unto Evil: I ſay not waiting in this, the Deſtroyer entred, and took Poſſeſſion, and uſurped Authority over both Soul and Body, and ſo both were defiled, while he whoſe right it was to reign, and unto whom both Soul and Body ſhould have yielded Subjection; I ſay, he ſtood without, knocking at the Door of my Heart, and this was his Love, and this was his Kindneſs, and this ingages me to love his Appearance; for the Lord waits that he may be gracious, notwithſtanding the many repulſes he meets withal, yet his Patience is lengthened out, and a hand of Love is ſtretched forth and extended even to thoſe that rebell againſt him, that he might have the Government of Man and Woman whoſe right it is to rule.</p>
            <p>But I was reſiſting his Appearance, and the Beaſt-like Nature was ſeeding over the Juſt, the Innocent, the Harmleſs Life, which as I may ſay, lay in the Manger, the Inn being taken up with other Gueſts, and ſo I was ſleighting the Lord's Viſitation of Love, and grieving his Holy Spirit, and crucifying to my ſelf afreſh the Son of God, and putting him unto open ſhame, and hereby was laying a ſtumbling-Block in the Way of others, through the ſubtil Wiles of the Evil One, who goes about ſeeking whom he may devour, intangle and anſnare by his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Stratagems and Devices whereby he lies in wait to deceive, and by being overcome of his Temptations, have I provoked the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58717:7"/>Lord, and laid a ſtumbling Block in the Way of others, and been prejudiciall to the Salvation of others, which cauſes me thus to write, that I may eaſe my ſelf, and clear my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this matter, for I have been regardleſs of my Words and Wayes, and ſometimes was eating and drinking with the Drunken, and ſo have been a Partaker of her Sin, and ſo partook of her Plagues, which will firſt or laſt come upon all, and ſeize upon all that ſin againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>And by ſinning againſt the Lord, I thereby expoſed the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Truth of God to be Contemned and Vilified, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof to be Reproached; and hereby have given Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Enemies of God's Truth, and Divine Light, who do of late, as formerly, <hi>ſeek Occaſion againſt this bleſſed Light;</hi> and are riſen up of late in great Rage againſt the Truth and the Profeſſors thereof, as if by their <hi>Dialogues,</hi> as the Title thereof implyes, they <hi>would <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian the whole Body of Friends,</hi> who have believed in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Head of his Church over all, God bleſſed forever and evermore; and ſo they have Blaſphemed God, and his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And alſo, I was Hardening others in Wickedneſs by ſinning againſt the Lord, &amp; ſo ſtrengthening the Hands of the Wicked. and rejoycing the Hearts of thoſe that live wantonly upon the Earth, and are Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, and are crucifying the juſt Principle in themſelves, which if they would let ariſe, it would diſperſe and ſcatter all thoſe thick Miſts, and that Darkneſs which has ſpread over Nations and People (in this <hi>Night of Apoſtacy</hi>) as it was ſaid, <hi>Let God ariſe, and his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſhall be ſcattered, and he ſhall conſume them with the Spirit of his Mouth, &amp; ſhall deſtroy with the Brightneſs of his Coming:</hi> and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord forever, a Remnant, whom the Lord hath drawn unto himſelf in ſome meaſure with the Cords of Love, are come to witneſs his <hi>Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs,</hi> whereby the Man of Sin comes to be weakened and worſted, and ſo the Lord comes to reign in <hi>Sion,</hi> and to turn away Ungodlineſs from <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſo Peace with the Lord comes again to be witneſſed.</p>
            <p>And alſo, I was Sadning the Hearts of the Righteous by Diſobeying the Lord, wherefore the Indignation of the Lord was againſt me, and his Righteous Judgments followed me, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58717:8"/>his Wrath begun to burn very hot againſt me, and the Terrors of the Lord, as I may ſay, even diſtracted me, that I was even at my Wits End, becauſe I had ſinned againſt the Lord, and was bound even Hand and Foot, as I may ſay, and caſt into Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and my Underſtanding was darkned, &amp; Wiſdom was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from me, even Wiſdom as a Man, becauſe I was gone from the Preſence of the Lord, and was not waiting upon him for Counſel and Inſtruction, inſomuch that at laſt I was even an Aſtoniſhment to my ſelf: and when I begun to conſider my Wayes and Doings, I ſaw, <hi>that the Hand of the Lord was lifted up againſt me, becauſe I was not watchful over my Words and Wayes, but was running out into Looſneſs and Vanity, and was ſometimes eating and Drinking with the Drunken;</hi> and I became even as a Prey to the Devourer, and Waſting and Deſtruction was in my Pathes, and Peace with the Lord I knew not; for I was ſinning againſt him, and grieving his holy Spirit, and ſo the Lord took no Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in me, as he hath ſaid in dayes paſt by his Servants; <hi>If any man draw back, my Soul ſhall have no Pleaſure in him;</hi> and ſo I became a Reproach among the <hi>Heathen,</hi> &amp; a Scorn unto Fools, and was Unfaithful to the Lord, and was not a Faithful Steward in what was committed to my Charge, &amp; was not Honouring the Lord as I ought, nor anſwering his Requirings; but was doing that which was Diſhonourable unto him, and to the Truth which I did profeſs, and was not waiting in the Light, whereby I might have witneſſed a profitting in the Fear &amp; Wiſdom of the Lord: <hi>For, the Fear of the Lord, that is Wiſdom, and a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding have all they that wait in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in their ownhearts,</hi> that ſo they may depart from that which is Evil; that will both diſcover ſin, and give Dominion over it, as it is believed in and obeyed, and then <hi>the Willing and the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient will eat the Good of the Land,</hi> and this is the Portion of them that obey the Voice of the Lord: And thus, ſo far as I have been obedient, have I witneſſed <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp; in the Lord's Preſence is <hi>Life,</hi> but out of his Preſence is <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs, Diſtreſs</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh, but at his Right-hand are Rivers of Pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now the Rebe Ilious and Diſobedient, which will not how to the Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus in their own hearts, but live in Pride and pleaſure upon the Earth, and ſo are rejoycing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58717:8"/>in a thing of naught, the Glory whereof ſhall ſoon fade and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away, and are crucifying and piercing the Juſt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying the Lord, <hi>they muſt dwell in a dry Land, and Torment and Wo muſt unavoidably be the Portion of all they that will not come unto the Lord, and ſubmit to his Government, whoſe Government is a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Government, and his Law is the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo let not any ſleight the <hi>Day of God's Viſitation;</hi> for this is the Day of God's Love, wherein he is ſtretching forth the <hi>Arm of his Love and Mercy to gather people out of the crocked Wayes and by-Pathes unto himſelf;</hi> to which end the Lord appears, and ſhews unto man his Sin and Iniquity, which keeps the Soul in Bondage and Slavery, for ſo I have found it to be: I ſay, <hi>That that reproves man for ſin in the inward parts muſt be minded &amp; obey'd by all that deſire to have Peace with the Lord:</hi> for this ſame <hi>Light,</hi> which many are vilifying and reproaching, is <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Light of the World,</hi> and is that <hi>Great Prophet</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake of in dayes paſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, like unto me, him ſhall you hear in all things; and whoever will not hear him, ſhall be cut off from among my People:</hi> And ſo, let every one come to hear this Great Prophet, and obey his Voice, that ſo the Land may be cleanſed of Evil-doers; <hi>For when the Righteous bears Rule, the Land rejoyces; but when the Wicked bears Rule, the Land mourns</hi> (juſt ſo) And here I ſpeak not of things at a diſtance, or becauſe it is thus written, but what I find in my own particular to be true; bleſſed be the Name of our God, who is <hi>Light,</hi> and let him be exalted and magnified above &amp; over all forever &amp; evermore.</p>
            <p>And ſo knowing the <hi>Terrors of the Lord becauſe of ſin,</hi> I would perſwade all to wait upon the <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp; then the Wicked ſhall not bear rule, but be judged and condemned by the <hi>Light,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the <hi>Power and Strength of the Lord;</hi> and ſo all to wait upon the Lord in the way of his <hi>Judgments,</hi> though the Flaming Sword turn ſo that the Tranſgreſſor cannot enter: yet wait upon God, and flee not his Righteous Judgments: for the Sword of the Lord is only drawn againſt the Tranſgreſſor in man, and as that comes to be cut down and burnt up: ſo an Entrance comes to be witneſſed again and Peace with the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be known; and this is the Way of <hi>Sions</hi> Redemption, as it is ſaid, Sion <hi>muſt be redeemed through Judgment, and her Converts through
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58717:9"/>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo Peace with the Lord will be known; <hi>for the Lord will ſpeak Peace to his People; but let not any turn again unto Folly,</hi> and Peace will be witneſſed by all they that lay hold of God's Everlaſting Strength, as the Lord hath ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, if any one will take hold of my Strength, and make Peace with me, he ſhall make Peace with me.</hi> Now Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, is the Wiſdom of God, the Power and Strength of God, and whoever takes hold of this divine Light which ſhines in the Heart, &amp; appears againſt Sin, they take hold of Gods' Strength, and will witneſs Peace with the Lord, as they keep unto it: and ſaith my Soul, Return thou never again unto Folly, but abide in the Light, and walk therein, and wait upon the Lord in the Way of his Judgments: <hi>For</hi> Sion <hi>muſt be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med through Judgment, and her Converts through Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo here is not a putting the Day of Judgment afar off, as the Profeſſors of our Age do, till after Death, or they know not when: but behold the Judge ſtands at the Door, that which reproves, that which convinces of Sin in the Heart, is that which muſt judge both Quick and Dead; <hi>for the Father judgeth no Man, but hath committed all Judgment unto the Son,</hi> and that which appears in the Hearts of Men and Women againſt Sin, and all manner of Evil, is the Son of Righteouſneſs which doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Hearts of Men and Women, and doth give a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of every one's State and Condition, <hi>as really as the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Created Light and Sun appears in the Outward World, and gives a Diſcovery of Perſons and Things; So really doth the Increated Light and Spiritual Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus ſhine in the Hearts of all whereby all as they come to receive of his Life, and partake of his Virtue, do as really grow and flouriſh in Holineſs, and are freſh and lively to the Lord, as any Outward Tree or Plant grows, that receives Influence from the Outward Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo this Son of Righteouſneſs will ariſe with Healing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Wings to them that fear him, and love his Appearance; <hi>For he Rejoyces in the Habitable Parts of the Earth, and his Delight is with the Sons of Men:</hi> But now here is the Reaſon why People and Nations are not healed, but Pride hath over-ſpread the Land, and Oppreſſion bears rule, and Drunkenneſs, and Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and War, and Blood-ſhed; and here is the Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58717:9"/>that maketh Deſolate, and this is the Cauſe why Iniquity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds: For though moſt are in a Profeſſion of Religion, ſome in one Way, and ſome in another; yet they have not God's Fear before their Eyes, and ſo are not mindful of the Lord, nor obedient to his Holy Commands, nor doing unto others as they would others ſhould do to them; but their minds are run out into the Earth, and are gone a whoring from the Lord, and ſo are not following the Lord, nor obeying his Voice, but provoaking the Lord to pour out his Vials of Wrath and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; and behold the many Vials of God's Fury and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, which have of late been poured forth: And hath not the Lord even overthrown and deſtroyed ſome, even as he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah?</hi> and hath the Remnant that eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Repented, and given Giory to the Lord? And at this very day is the Lord pleading with the Inhabitants of the Earth by Fire and by Sword, and his Hand is ſtretched forth ſtill, and the Lord hath ſent forth his Angels one after another with Vials of his Wrath and Indignation, and hath poured, and is pouring them out upon the Inhabitants of the Earth; yet where is that Repentance and for ſaking of ſin the Lord requires? And though many have been ſpared with their Lives, though they have been burnt out of their Houſes, yet as Proud as before, as Vain and Wicked as before, and ſo are abuſing God's Mercies, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voaking him to his very Face; and for theſe things the Lord hath a Controverſie with the Inhabitants of the Earth; becauſe they Repent not of their Deeds, therefore the Vials of God's Wrath are yet preparing to be poured out becauſe men are not preparing to meet the Lord by Repentance: And the Lord has determined to make a ſhort Work in the Earth, and to cut his Work ſhort in Righteouſneſs, and will yet plead with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth by Fire and by Sword, both inwardly and outwardly; and becauſe the Lord will do thus, let all that make mention of the Name of the Lord break off ſin ſpeedily, if it may be a lengthening out your Tranquility and Peace, and meet the Lord in the way of his Judgments, and bow before his Preſence; <hi>For the Lord will put an End to Sin, and finiſh Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs:</hi> and therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>Come out of her, my People, and be ye ſeparate, touch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58717:10"/>no unclean thing, and I will receive you; but all that will not come out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and be ſeparate, but partake of her Sins, they muſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of her Plagues:</hi> I ſpeak here of <hi>Myſtery Babylon, the Mother of Harlots, and of all the Abominations of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having a ſenſe of theſe things upon my heart and ſpirit, I do warn all, and intreat all, to come unto the Son of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which ſhines in the heart, and appears againſt ſin; and as many as are ſheltered here, and are gathered under the Wings of God's Power, here is ſafety, and no where elſe to be found. And this is the Day of the Lord that doth burn as an Oven, and all the Proud, and all that do Wickedly, and will not turn to the Lord ſhall be as Stubble, and ſhall be burnt up; and ſo the Determination of the Lord is, <hi>to put an End to ſin, and to exalt his Truth over all, and to bring ſwift Deſtruction upon the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Iniquity.</hi> Therefore Repent quickly, and break off your Sins by Righteouſneſs, leſt the Lord ſwear in his Wrath, <hi>that you ſhall never enter into his Reſt,</hi> and tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</p>
            <p>Now remember this, all you that have drawn back from the Lord, and for ſaken your <hi>firſt Love;</hi> and return unto the Lord before it be too late; for your Account will be dreadful, and <hi>his Spirit will not alwayes ſtrive with man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And remember theſe things, all you that are taking your fill of Pleaſure, and ſpending your precious time in Playes and Paſtimes, and Pride, and Vanity, in Rioting and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are in the Pollution of the World, and are gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fleſh, and living Wantonly upon Earth, and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Juſt in themſelves; let your Laughter be turned into Weeping, and your bravery of Attire into Sack-cloth, before the fierce Indignation of the Lord break forth, and there be no Remedy. Therefore now turn unto the Lord, before your Day be over, and your Sun ſet, and while you find any thing ſtriving in your hearts againſt Sin, againſt Pride, againſt Drunkenneſs, againſt Covetouſneſs and Earthly mindedneſs; I ſay, while you find any thing ſtriving in your hearts againſt ſin, embrace that that appears againſt ſin, love it, cheriſh it, and you will find a Growth and Encreaſe in Holineſs; but if you reject it, if you ſleight it, and rebel againſt it, it will ſet upon you, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58717:10"/>groſs Darkneſs will overtake you, and you will come to be a Habitation for every Foul and Unclean ſpirit, and never come to know a Habitation in God, nor a Place of Reſt when Time ſhall be no more: <hi>But Wo and Torment forever and evermore will be the Portion of all thoſe that Rebel againſt the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in their own hearts, and will not Return unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo having pretty well eas'd my ſelf, and clear'd my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this Matter, I have little more to ſay at preſent, only to warn all, and intreat all (to mind the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, that reproves man of ſin) even thoſe, I ſay, that hitherto have been Quarelling and Contending againſt the Light, and have, as it were ſounded an Alarum of War in the Ears of the people to Battel (either by printing or otherwiſe) againſt the Light of Chriſt, the Lamb of God, which takes away the ſin of the World, and againſt the Followers of the Lamb; but behold, the Lamb and the Saints muſt have the Victory: And though many Weapons have been formed againſt <hi>Sion,</hi> yet none ſhall proſper. And what though the <hi>Heathen</hi> rage, and the Wicked (who are gone from the Preſence and Appearance of God in themſelves) imagine a vain thing, yet the Lord ſits in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and laughs at them, he will have them in Deriſion; and the Evil that is done to <hi>Sion,</hi> it will be upon <hi>Babylon;</hi> for it is a Righteous Thing with God, <hi>To Recompence Tribulation to them that Trouble his People:</hi> Therefore Repent of all your Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and Rage, and turn unto the Lord, before it be too late, and ſlight not God's Love.</p>
            <p>And whereas in this Book thoſe concerned as Authors of that <hi>Dialogue</hi> are charged as being guilty of <hi>Blaſphemy and Rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his People;</hi> if they ſhall object and ſay, <hi>This Charge is not ſufficient to prove any ſuch thing:</hi> I refer them to thoſe Books, which have of late been publiſhed concerning them, wherein their Blaſphemy and Rage, their ſelf-Contradictions, Lyes and SLanders are ſufficiently proved, and alſo their Injuſtice (to the People of God called <hi>Quakers</hi>) manifeſted. And as to that particular wherein my Name is brought to publick View, I ſay it is a Lye and Slander.</p>
            <p>And whereas he hath ſaid, I denyed that Chriſt which was born of the Virgin and died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and called him <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58717:11"/>I do declare and teſtifie that I do confeſs and unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly believe that that Chriſt which was born of the Virgin, and was crucifyed at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was and is the true Chriſt, the Son of the Living God, whom the Father hath ſent into the World, and that whoever believes in him, ſhall not periſh, but be ſaved from Sin, and obtain Eternal Life by him.</p>
            <p>And now let all and every one of us mind the Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus, that diſcovers and reproves ſin when no Eye outwardly ſees, for on this wiſe have I known God's Appearance againſt ſin, and his Righteous Judgment becauſe of Iniquity. And let none content themſelves with a bare Profeſſion of the Truth it ſelf; for this will not bring Peace to the Soul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Poſſeſſion and Life of Truth it ſelf; and herein ſtands the Fellowſhip and Communion of the Saints, it is in Obedience to the Lord: and ſo let all &amp; every one that makes mention of the Name of the Lord depart from Iniquity; &amp; let none cumber their Minds with the many things, nor yet mind things too high for them; for hereby the Evil One will have an Advantage againſt you: Therefore wait upon the Lord for Counſel and Advice in all things, and ſo we ſhall be preſerved from the many Snares and Intanglements, which they are ſubject to who have their Minds abroad, and are gadding &amp; going aftray from the Light So let us all give heed to this Light, that we may ſerve the Lord the remainer of our dayes in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, that ſo we may lay down our Heads in Peace, and forever be with the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Southwark, <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 10th <hi>Day of the 7th Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,</hi> 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Richard Stubbs.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58717:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
